Seeing of the model, especially until the authority board meeting for May 16, 2022, the application model.
That's your one-chirped herb note.
Let's pray.
Oh, they got a week thank you, Lord, for your blessings over this community, over this
Lord got over our elected officials, praying out for your guidance, and your wisdom, Father, we pray
for your favor on this town, got to pray that you'll bless us, got to send businesses
our way of blessing the businesses that are here, got to guide each and every decisions
May we pray that you'll honor and glorify your name in Christ and we do pray.
Amen.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the Republic for which it stands,
one nation, under God, and in the middle, who would live a team and justice for all.
Number four, public input of the personal appearances, of the five, consent and into
the staff recommends we approve item six and seven.
Question two approved?
Second.
E7.
Hi.
David.
Parker.
Hi.
Eight.
Good day, I'll straighten.
And David, David's right from any claim from your day, every licensee.
So, may our members of the council, you'll find in your pack as a purchaser related to the
call of relicencing project and rule curve.
So this is actually a combination of three separate invoices.
The total of the purchase order is $77,492.70.
There are two separate invoices from Davis' right to Maine in one from Goodell, Stratton.
And again, these invoices are for legal fees related to the Pins' Call of Relicencing Project
and rule curve change.
And so before the council votes on this item, I'd like to take some time for a minute and kind
of break down and explain a lot of the city's efforts on going efforts related to these legal
issues and it's quite a complex situation.
So hopefully I can shed some light on it and not just confuse everybody and hopefully Jack and Larry
will be patient with me who are two of the most knowledgeable individuals on this who are in the crowd.
So this can be a little bit intimidating with those folks across, but I'll do my best.
The background on these GRDA related issues go back quite a bit.
And I know it's a very complex item and should not be taken lightly.
We also have to be sensitive to the fact that these are active legal matters.
And elements, it's not always appropriate to discuss all of our leads.
legal issues and elements in a open meeting, so be patient with me as I kind of refer to
my notes and make sure I stay on target.
I do often provide updates when related purchasers and invoices for legal fees appear
on our agenda.
So, if you go where have this refer to it, be patient with me.
There are three distinct legal areas related to GRDA in which the city contracts for legal
and engineering expertise.
These three are the civil litigation, our appeal to FERC regarding current license violations
and GRDA's re-licensing of the Pinscolon Dam.
FERC, who you'll hear me refer to often, is the federal energy regulatory commission
who's responsible for the federal oversight of GRDA.
So to explain further, the first area is the civil litigation.
This is also known as the city's lawsuit against GRDA.
There are about 250 units or properties in about 450 plaintiffs represented in this lawsuit,
most of which live in the city limits.
The city is only one of those 450 plaintiffs.
In totality, all claims combined in the civil lawsuit is in the neighborhood of around $100 million
for all again for all plaintiffs.
However, the city's claim is only for $3.2 million of that $100 million.
Although the city has not paid any attorney fees, many years ago, the city did agree
to front $300,000 for engineering and surveys that have been used in the civil litigation.
So again, the city has not just declared the city has not paid any attorney fees for the city's
lawsuit against GRDA.
The second area is the appeal.
This is the city of my, my, my, my, the federal energy regulatory commission in the U.S. Court
of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit case number 20-1325.
The appeal is related to a complaint filed by the city with FERC in 2018, where the city
has FERC to enforce the provisions of the current GRDA license, which states that GRDA must
acquire the rights to all lands and floods.
It is, in fact, GRDA is, in this, it is, in fact, that GRDA is in violation of this particular
current license.
FERC, however, decided to kick the can down the road and not deal with these violations of the
current license and instead address them in the relationship process.
Stating the city did not provide sufficient evidence of upstream flooding, knowing the
everlasting process and is often delayed, and in one instance it is delayed for about 24
years.
So, we knew the city could not wait that long so the city did.
to appealed the decision to the DC Circuit Court of Appeals in March of 2020.
The city of the city's appeal outlined a series of misrepresentations, promises, and changes
of positions taken by GDRDA over the last several decades regarding the flooding in and around
by Emma.
It also argued that FERC ignored the evidence of flooding presented by the city and that
the Court should order FERC to order GDRDA to comply with current license.
In their response of briefs, GDRDA argued that the matter should be deferred to the
relicencing process, FERC also argued that the matter should be deferred to relicencing
and that it adequately considered the city's evidence of flooding.
The city filed its reply brief disputing those arguments on July 6th and oral arguments
took place in December of last year.
In January of this year, the DC Circuit Court ruled in the city's favor stating that
FERC's argument that the GDRDA had not violated its operating license was surprisingly
unpersuasive.
The Court found that while the city provided powerful evidence that the GDRDA's principal in Dam caused
had caused flooding in the city, and that FERC had conducted a thorough analysis of its review.
So we are now waiting for FERC to review as remained by the DC Circuit Court.
This was a very big deal.
In fact, I've got some articles that were written in the law 360, during that if you get a chance
you need to take a look at and we probably wish I had enough copies to hand out everybody,
but if anybody wants a copy of one, provide one.
Maybe I like a copy.
It's a very well written article, you know, law up here review that just kind of outlines and explains
the court case and the findings and they just, they did a very good job because it is a very complex.
So the third and final area is the re-license.
And to add insult to injury, GDRDA has filed its application for re-license of the Pinsco Dam requesting
their application to essentially raise the leg level by another two feet.
As published in the Tulsa World on January 9th of 2020, GDRDA has also requested the license
be for a period of 50 years instead of the current 30 years.
So you can imagine how this can greatly emphasize the importance of this process, this
re-licensing process.
There are ongoing technical studies being conducted by GDRDA as required.
by FERC and outlined in a detailed study plan. We are evaluating these studies and results
every step of the way to ensure that the impact of my image is understood and considered.
There are public technical conferences where we have an opportunity to ask questions and raise concerns.
These technical conferences are attended by FERC, City of Miami, and our experts,
several tribes, tribal leaders, and their legal experts, the wildlife department,
Rebecca Jam and the Lead Organization and many other stakeholders who understand the importance of this situation.
To date, the issues that concerns raised by the city have resulted in significant changes to the
study plan and shown a light on the serious issues of flooding upstream. If we do nothing,
then we are blindly accepting the outcome of the re-licensing and whatever GRDA wants to do with the
lake levels and the operations of the dam. Related to settlement offers, it should be pointed out
that over the last year, myself, and many others, have met with GRDA leadership many times in search of
solutions to our civil lawsuit. Today, there have been no official settlement offers made. Even though
our lead attorney regarding the FERC matter has made it clear to the GRDA lead attorney that the city
is open to settlement offers. Regarding expenses that we've incurred over the life of some of these legal
issues, just to provide some history related to the fiscal impact, the city's record show,
the expenses as far back as 2008, totaling around 3.5 million. That's for legal and engineering expenses.
Not all of that is even legal expenses, but a combination of legal and engineering
combining the expenses for all of these efforts. Now, again, any of the legal expenses that
we've paid for were for the appeal and re-licensing, but nothing no legal fees have been paid for the
city's lawsuit. The per kind of a point of reference, however, the myime-especially utility
pays GRDA around 700,000 to 1.2 million every month for power. That is more than we spend in
an entire fiscal year defending ourselves. Our community in economy has lost millions due to flooding
and flood damage, our citizens spend thousands on flood insurance, and no one can afford more flooding
or for FEMA to raise the flood map yet again, including even more properties in the flood zone.
This would result in further lowering our property values, and we all agree that the legal issues
have been going on for many, many years, but honestly, for the first time, myime-es being heard in the concerns
are being heard.
the way to the federal court. And I could assume that GRDA would love for the community to lose
faith and become distracted or let our guard down. But this is not the time to throw in the
towel and roll over. There is just way too much at stake for the city of Miami. You must consider
the past, the future impact, and our current efforts for decades to come. So closing, I should also
make note that the city is also working on ways to be more flood resilient. So besides just
our legal approach, this includes applying for the building resilient infrastructure and communities
to raise various roads around Miami, as well as the DR4575 City of Miami mitigation of roadway flooding
to raise roads. The city has also been working with the Department of Transportation to raise highways
around Miami. And the city is working with one of our engineers, Tectrere Tech, who recently
completed a levee survey or feasibility study that will be presented in coming months. I also want
to note that it would be my recommendation to anyone that's interested in learning more about this in
these GRDA matters. A 10-up coming town hall meeting that has been scheduled for Friday, June 10th.
At 7 p.m. here at City Hall, this is something that Larry Bork has been working with all of the
different plaintiffs involved in those stakeholders involved across the city to pull this together.
He's been working on this several weeks and they finally knelt down a date. And so I think we need to
make every effort possible now to get the word out when this is June 10th 7 p.m. I make sure that
everyone in the community attends because we'll have all the experts there. We'll have the historians
of our community that have involved with this for years. And the goal is to share all the information that
we can answer questions and educate the community again on why we continue to be in the position we're in
and why it's so important that the city of Miami would be heard. Defend ourselves and make our issues
known. So with that, I appreciate you all for your patience with my long answer, but I'm happy to
answer any questions you might have. I'm still in your motion. I'm still in your motion.
other new business, if any, which is really supposed to be this agenda.
TAN staff report, 11 trustee community announcements, 12 adjournment.
Come in.
Thank you.